<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A thanksgiving-sermon for the peace preach'd at the parish-church of St. Dunstan's in the West, Dec. IId, 1697 / by William Gallaway ... ; printed at the particular request of some of the hearers.</title>
            <author>Gallaway, William, fl. 1692-1697.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 37 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A41963</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G180</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37390</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">16437907</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 16437907</idno>
            <idno type="VID">105395</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A41963)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 105395)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1093:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A thanksgiving-sermon for the peace preach'd at the parish-church of St. Dunstan's in the West, Dec. IId, 1697 / by William Gallaway ... ; printed at the particular request of some of the hearers.</title>
                  <author>Gallaway, William, fl. 1692-1697.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 23 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Hugh Newman ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Half-title reads: Mr. Gallaway's thanksgiving-sermon for the peace.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Isaiah XIV, 16-18 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Peace --  Religious aspects --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:105395:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A <hi>Thankſgiving-Sermon</hi> FOR THE PEACE PREACH'D At the Pariſh-Church of St. <hi>Dunſtan</hi>'s in the <hi>Weſt, Dec.</hi> II<hi rend="sup">d.</hi> 1697.</p>
            <p>By <hi>William Gallaway,</hi> A. M. Chaplain to the Officers, and others, of <hi>His Majeſty</hi>'s <hi>TRAIN</hi> of <hi>ARTILLERY.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed at the particular Requeſt of ſome of the Hearers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi> Printed for <hi>Hugh Newman,</hi> at the <hi>Graſhopper</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey.</hi> 1697.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:105395:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105395:2"/>
            <p>Mr. <hi>GALLAWAY</hi>'s <hi>Thankſgiving-Sermon</hi> FOR THE PEACE.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:105395:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:105395:3"/>
            <head>A Thanks-Giving SERMON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſaiah XIVth. 16, 17, 18 Verſes.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>They that ſee thee, ſhall narrowly look upon thee, and conſider thee, ſaying, Is this the Man that made the Earth to Tremble, that did ſhake Kingdoms? that made the World as a Wilderneſs, and deſtroyed the Cities thereof, that opened not the Houſe of his Priſoners? All the Kings of the Nations, even all of them lie in Glory, every one in his own Houſe.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IN the Beginning of this <hi>Chapter, Iſaiah,</hi> by his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetick Spirit, foretells the Merciful Deliverance that God would bring to paſs for the Houſe of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> that the Time was near at hand, That <hi>the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogancy
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:105395:4"/>of the Proud was to ceaſe, and that the Haughtineſs of the Terrible was to be laid low,</hi> as it is in the 13th <hi>Chapter,</hi> 11th <hi>Verſe,</hi> that there would be an Unexpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Change in the Face of Affairs, and that the Lord would not only give <hi>them Reſt from their Sorrows, and from their Fears, and from their Hard Bondage, wherein they were made to ſerve,</hi> Verſe the 3d, but alſo, as a Viſible Mark of his Great Favour, and more Abundant Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, He declares, <hi>They ſhall take them Captives, whoſe Captives they were, and they ſhall Rule over their Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours:</hi> And as a full confirmation of this Joyful Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, the Prophet further aſſures them, in the 24, 25, 26, 27 Verſes. <hi>The Lord of Hosts hath Sworn, ſaying, Surely as I have thought, ſo ſhall it come to paſs; and, as I have purpoſed, ſo ſhall it ſtand. That I will break the</hi> Aſſyrian <hi>in my Land, and upon my Mountains tread him underfoot: then ſhall his Yoke depart from off them, and his Burden depart from off their Shoulders. This is the purpoſe that is purpoſed on the whole Earth: and this is the hand that is ſtretched out upon all the Nations. For the Lord of Hoſts hath purpoſed, and who ſhall diſanul it? and his hand is ſtretched out, and who ſhall turn it back?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the Infallible Aſſurance of this Extraordinary Event it was, that the Prophet repreſents the <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites,</hi> with their Neighbouring Kings, who labour'd under the ſame Tyrannical Oppreſſions, thus Inſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting over the King of <hi>Babylon; How hath the Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour ceaſed? The Lord hath broken the Staff of the Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the Scepter of the Rulers. The whole Earth is at reſt and is quiet, they break forth into Singing. All they (the Kings of the Nations) ſhall ſpeak and ſay unto thee Art thou alſo become weak as we? Art thou become like unto us? Thy Pomp is brought down to the Grave. How
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:105395:4"/>art thou fallen from Heaven, O Lucifer, Son of the Morning! How art thou cut down to the ground which didſt weaken the Nations? For thou haſt ſaid in thine heart, I will aſcend into Heaven, I will exalt my Throne above the Stars of God, I will aſcend above the heights of the Clouds, I will be like the Moſt High; yet thou ſhalt be brought down to Hell, to the ſides of the Pit.</hi> Thus the <hi>Context,</hi> which leads me to the words of my <hi>Text, They that ſee thee ſhall narrowly look upon thee, and conſider thee: They,</hi> who were formerly amaz'd with thy Glit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering Outſide, with thy Vain and Oſtentatious Boaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, ſhall View, and Reflect, with Surprize, on thy Unforeſeen and Unexpected Change; <hi>They,</hi> ſhall be Curious, and Inquiſitive, as if Amaz'd at the Unap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended Cauſes of this thy Sudden Alteration; and the more eſpecially at their Wits end, conſidering their Eares were every day fill'd with the Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, but empty Noiſes of thoſe who had only flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd Thee Invincible and Immortal. <hi>They</hi> ſhall <hi>conſider,</hi> That the Lord of Hoſts can, and will <hi>puniſh the fruit of the ſtout Heart of the King of Aſſyria, and the Glory of his High Looks,</hi> (whom he before Rais'd up, as the Rod of his Anger, to Scourge the Hypocritical and Idolatrous <hi>Iſraelites</hi>) notwithſtanding he hath ſaid, Chapter the 10th, 13th Verſe, <hi>By the ſtrength of my hand I have done it, and by my Wiſdom, for I am Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent: I have remov'd the Bounds of the People, and have robbed their Treaſures. I have put down the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants like a Valiant Man.</hi> Tho' thou didſt fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aſcribe all thy Succeſs and Victories to the Strength of thine <hi>Own</hi> Arm and Martial Conduct, yet now the Deliver'd Inſultingly deſpiſe thee, and ſay, <hi>Is this the Man that made the Earth to Tremble, that did ſhake King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms? That made the World as a Wilderneſs, and deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:105395:5"/>the Cities thereof, that open'd not the Houſe of his Priſoners?</hi> Is the Grand Monarch of <hi>Aſſyria</hi> Dwindled into this Contemptible State? Is the Scourge of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind grown Feeble and Weak, unable to carry on his Terrible Sieges, and All-deſtroying Devaſtations? Are all his Subtle and Powerful Efforts and Contrivan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces to Enſlave the World at an end? And are thy Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons open to all but thoſe who will not fall down and Worſhip the Images of <hi>(New) Babylon?</hi> And <hi>do all the Kings of the Nations, even all of them lye in Glory, every one in his own Houſe?</hi> Are thy Conqueſts ceas'd, and art thou now forc'd to Diſmantle, and Reſtore with Shame and Regret, the Dear, but Short-liv'd Poſſeſſion of what was Purchaſt, with ſo much La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, ſo much Treaſure, and ſo much Blood? How art thou Mortify'd to behold thine Enemies, whom thou not long ſince didſt trample on, and deſpiſe, Reinſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in their own Envy'd Cities and Territories? to be thus Gratingly Lowr'd from thy High Slippery Station, and to have thy Miſtaken Greatneſs, and Falſe Glory, go out like a Dazling Meteor, or Blazing Comet; What Admiration! What Wonder! ſhall not theſe Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons fill them with, who <hi>narrowly look on thee, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider thee:</hi> Thus the Prophet Elegantly and Inſulting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſcribes the Mean Appearance, and little Figure, of the not long before Mighty Monarch of <hi>Aſſyria;</hi> which indeed, if duly obſerv'd, is a proper Inſtance for Mankind in General, to ſhew the Inſtability of Humane Greatneſs; and to Princes more particularly Inſtructive, to lay aſide their Ambitious Projects of Swelling their Power beyond its proper Limits, by Unjuſt and Unnatural Means, at the Ruine and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery of their Fellow-Creatures; Conſidering withall, that the true end of all Power, is only to capacitate
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:105395:5"/>us to do the more Good in the World, to Relieve and Support the Oppreſs'd, and not to Cruſh and Oppreſs. Thus having taken a Tranſient View, as to the Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion and Deſign of the Words of my Text, I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to Deduce, and clear this General Propoſition or Obſervation from them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt.</hi> The Viſibility of Providence in the Great and Unexpected Revolutions of Kingdoms and Empires.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly.</hi> Reflect on, and Apply them, with Refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the Solemnity of this Day.</p>
            <p>That there is a Supreame and Independent <hi>Being</hi> which Created and Governs all things in Heaven and Earth, is a Truth which hath been ſo Univerſally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd, that I preſume I need not be at much pains to convince and confirm it: The Light of Nature, and that of Reaſon, together with thoſe viſible Revelations that God hath made of himſelf to the Nation and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and as above all the clear and undenia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble manifeſtation of himſelf in, and by the Goſpel; are Evidences that carry ſo much conviction as hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be reſiſted, and that which gives it a double force, 'tis only deny'd by thoſe whoſe diſſolute Lives and diſturb'd Conſciences falſely, but fatally, forces them to deny that provok'd Being they fear and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at; and 'tis hardly poſſible, but that a Man muſt firſt be a Practical, before he can be ſo fooliſh as to own himſelf a Speculative Atheiſt. <hi>Seneca</hi> the <hi>Roman Moraliſt</hi> tells us, There is no Nation ſo Barbarous as not to believe ſome Gods; the moſt Savage own a
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:105395:6"/>Supreame Power and <hi>Being,</hi> tho' they miſtake in the true object of their Service and Adoration. How can we account for the Original and continuance of this World, and all things in it, unleſs we come to the Acknowledgement of ſome Independent and Almighty <hi>Being,</hi> the firſt cauſe of it? For what is Created and finite muſt neceſſarily be produc'd and ſubſiſt by ſome uncreated and infinite power; and St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells the <hi>Romans, Chap.</hi> 1. v. 20. <hi>That the inviſible things of him from the Creation of the World are clearly ſeen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing underſtood by the things that are made, even his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Power and Godhead; ſo that they are without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe.</hi> 'Tis as unreaſonable to believe that the moſt exact Order and Harmony of things ſhould be the product and effect of Jumbl'd and Confus'd Atoms, as that the curious motions of a Clock ſhould have its perfection from the bare Materials without the skillful hand and regular deſign of the Artiſt. God is the great Artificer (if I may ſo ſpeak) of the World, and all its various Intricate and Admirable Motions are kept going true by his Irreſiſtible Power and Wiſe Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. He hath made the Sun to rule by day, and the Moon by night, the Elements obſerve their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct Order, and all things Obey the Inſtinct and Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency of their Natures, unleſs otherwiſe commanded to demonſtrate the Glory and Power of their Great Lord and Creator. I ſhall not enlarge my diſcourſe on this point, only I thought it neceſſary to premiſe the acknowledgment of that Being, which muſt be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of in the proſecution of that Subject I am Enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in.</p>
            <p>The Three Cheif Attributes of God, are His <hi>Good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſs, Wiſdom,</hi> and <hi>Power;</hi> by theſe He is Kind and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:105395:6"/>Propitious, contrives and executes all thoſe things which are Beneficial to Mankind; upon which account 'tis one of the cheifeſt Bleſſings we enjoy in this our Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Pillgrimage, that an <hi>Immenſe, Good, All-Wiſe, and Allmighty God</hi> Governs the World, this is that peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar Bleſſing which raiſes our dejected Hopes, baniſhes our diſturbing Fears, and only affords us True and Solid comfort in our greateſt Extremities and Diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. In Him we Live, Move, and have our Being, and the influences of his Providences we enjoy with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out meaſure or intermiſſion. Is there any Good hath happen'd to us of which he hath not been the ſole Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor? Hath there been any deliverance which he with his own Right Hand hath not wrought for us? And are we not at this time delivered from our Open, and ſhellter'd under the ſhadow of his Wings from our conceal'd Enemies? Therefore we are more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially oblig'd to confeſs and own with thankfullneſs his Being and Care over us.</p>
            <p>'Tis to heighten the circumſtances of our preſent Joy, to reflect and reveiw our not long ſince Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholly proſpect of Affairs before our happy Revoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; When the powers of darkneſs at home, with the united ſtrength and Policy of our late Enemy had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triv'd and reſolv'd either our Perverſſion or Deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; then our Souls were overſpread with Black and Dreadful Clouds of Horrour and Darkneſs, Our Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits grew low and fainting, our hearts dejected, our knees trembling and beating againſt each other; then all our promiſing Hopes vaniſh'd, and our diſmal Fears encreas'd, our Circumſtances appear'd on all ſides ſo deſperate that our Reaſon and Faith were ſtagger'd and confounded to propoſe or believe which
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:105395:7"/>way or by what means we were to be reſcued from hoſe imminent dangers we were ſurrounded with; When behold, on a ſuddain, and in the midſt of our Diſtreſſes, God commands a deliverer to come unto us to aſſert and maintain our Rights, to preſerve that Church againſt whoſe Faith founded on a Rock (we have Chriſt's Promiſe) the gares of Hell ſhall not prevail. The time would fail me to enumerate the many ſignal and remarkable Providences which at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended that ſurprizing Revolution, of which barely to relate the Story is to recount them; Providences as viſible as the Sun at noon day, and like its rays darted round about us, only deny'd and ſlighted by ſome who were infatuated and blinded by their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts and others who were ignorant of our Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, and had deceiv'd themſelves into an opinion that <hi>Wolves</hi> and <hi>Foxes</hi> had a right to Lord it over our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Paſtures. Nor were theſe their devices only defeated at this critical time, but as our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs'd Enemies ſtill purſu'd and carry'd on their Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheivous Purpoſes, ſo we have advantagiouſly experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented the continued effects of Guarding and Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Providence over the Perſon and Affairs of our Undaunted deliverer. What Hazards hath he not been expos'd to both abroad and at home? Yet God hath ſtill preſerv'd him to Triumph over his Ungrateful Enemies; and tho' his and our pretended Friends have been long labouring to deſtroy and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray us by the moſt refin'd artifices of Embarraſſing and Entangling our Affairs, yet by his extraordinary Patience, and Sagacious conduct, together with that Over-ruleing Power, that hath brought Good out of their intended Evil, and turn'd their deſign'd Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs on their own Heads, we are hitherto Preſerv'd
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:105395:7"/>and Enjoy this envy'd opportunity of Praiſing and Adoring the Great Governour of the Univerſe, and of paying our juſt Homage of Thanks and Allegiance to his Vicegerent here below.</p>
            <p>Nothing is more evident to Obſervation, then that the thoughts of the generality of Mankind are taken up for the moſt part with the outward appearances of things, frighted and amaz'd with Humane Proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities, and what Humane Power is able to effect or bring to paſs, the uttmoſt efforts and ſtrengths of which are blown away like a bubble, with the leaſt blaſting breath of the Allmighty. He who hath ſet bounds to the impetuous and Maſterleſs Waves, with a commanding Nod, can ſtop the progreſs of the moſt ſwelling Tyrant. An Army of Frogs or Caterpillars can humble and deſtroy a proud <hi>Pharoah,</hi> as well as a powerful Hoſt of well diſciplin'd and Valiant Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers. The leaſt inſect in Nature can execute what his Infinite Wiſdome deſigns, and his Immenſe Power commands; ſo that we muſt all confeſs and declare with the Prophet <hi>David, Happy and Safe are the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> (and they only ſo) <hi>who have the Lord for their God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Works of Providence are fram'd in the depth of God's Wiſdome, and like as the ſilent and unſeen Waters, wandring in ſecret and diſtant Channels be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath the Surface of the Earth, at laſt meet together, and guſh into a Fountain. So the diverſity of Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions the Humours of Men, the Intreſts of Princes, the Intreagues of States, the Differences in Families, with a Thouſand little accidents, conſpire together to perfect and bring to light the deſign'd Work.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:105395:8"/>
            <p>What Alterations and Revolutions the Heathens of old, and our more Modern Politicians attribute to blind Fate, or inconſtant Fortune; by a more curious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection and enquiry will appear deſign'd and wrought by an All-ſeeing Eye, and ſteady Hand. For the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence of unforeſeen and unobſerv'd cauſes perfected and manifeſted in their viſible and wonderful Effects; ſtrikes and affects the Senſes and underſtandings of Men with Surprize and Amazement; but when they give themſelves leave to reflect and deliberate on the whole Tranſaction, it forces them to admire, as well as own the Powerful Finger of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Babylon,</hi> the Praiſe of the whole Earth, confident in her formidable Army inſtead of a Garriſon, her Inexhauſtible Stores as if provided for an Age, not a Seige; Her Walls like Pyramids and ſo numerous as if in one you had attack'd many Cities. How ſoon were her mighty Men ſlain and all her boaſted Strengths and Glories level'd and laid in the duſt? God's ſpecial Providence foretold by the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah</hi> in the 50 <hi>Chap.</hi> and 45th. verſe, <hi>Therefore hear ye the Counſel of the Lord that he hath taken againſt Babylon, and his Purpoſes that he hath Purpoſed againſt the Land of the Caldeans.</hi> In the 25th. verſe 'tis call'd, <hi>The Work of the Lord God of Hosts,</hi> and in the 27th. verſe, <hi>Wo unto them for their day is come, the time of their Viſitation,</hi> and in the 51ſt. Chap. 11th. verſe, <hi>The Lord hath raiſed up the Spirit of the Kings of the Medes for his Device is against Babylon to deſtray it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From which inſtance this obſervation occurs, That the <hi>greateſt</hi> Warlike Preparations cannot ſecure an Empire,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:105395:8"/>or City from Ruine, when the Counſel of the Lord hath otherwiſe determin'd it.</p>
            <p>From the Aſhes of the <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> or <hi>Aſſirian</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, that of the <hi>Medes</hi> or <hi>Perſians</hi> took its riſe or birth, nor is the ſhort time of its duration to be wonder'd at, if we conſider 'twas wholly plung'd and immers'd in the abounding Delicacies and Luxuries of the Eaſt (a certain Symtom of a Short-liv'd Empire) nay her Men were arriv'd to that degree of Softneſs and Effeminacy that their very Natures ſeem'd to be chang'd, and as the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah</hi> expreſſes it of the <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> Men, they were become as Women. When Deſtruction was coming upon them like a Whirlewind then they ſeem'd moſt ſecure, and fancy'd themſelves Victorious; and that Army, to quench whoſe Thirſts whole Rivers ſcarcely ſuffic'd, How ſoon was it defeated by a deſpis'd handful of Rugged <hi>Grecians,</hi> ſuppos'd only the forerunners or Forlorn-Hope, but led on by a dareing and Conquering <hi>Alexander;</hi> which plainly exemplifies, that the moſt unequal Numbers cannot command Victory, and that Conduct and Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage being put in the Ballance with the few will make them Superiour. Nor was Providence altogether unconcern'd in this great and extraordinary Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw, for the Prophet <hi>Daniel</hi> was foretold the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termin'd event in a Viſion, as appears from the 10th. <hi>Chap.</hi> 20th. verſe. <hi>Then ſaid he, Knoweſt thou wherefore I am come unto thee? And now will I return to fight with the Prince of Perſia, and when I am gone forth ſo, the Prince of Grecia ſhall come.</hi> God raiſed the Spirit of this great Prince, to attempt and execute what, in Humane Probability, ſeem'd unlikely, and little leſs then impoſſible to be effected; for who can imagine
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:105395:9"/>that 30 or 40000 Men ſhould be able to give a total defeat to a Million? the truth of which is confirm'd by all Hiſtorys, and this fatal blow put an end to the <hi>Perſian</hi> Empire.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Grecian</hi> which ſucceeded expir'd in its Infancy, whoſe extenſive Conqueſts were ſhar'd amongſt the Favourites and Officers of their Generous Maſter, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming what we read in the 11th. of <hi>Daniel,</hi> the 3d. and 4th. <hi>verſes, And a mighty King ſhall ſtand up, that ſhall rule with great Dominion and do according to his Will, and when he ſhall ſtand up his Kingdom ſhall be broken, and ſhall be divided towards the four Winds of Heaven, and not to his Posterity nor according to his Dominion which he ruled, For his Kingdom ſhall be pluck'd up even for others beſides thoſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The All-wiſe Providence of God pulls down one Empire and raiſes another, the Cauſes and Reaſons only known to himſelf; and for what end and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes, the ſhort line of our finite reaſon, and weak underſtandings is altogether incapable to reach and cannot fathom.</p>
            <p>But, amongſt all <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> nothing ſeems more Incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible, then the Riſe and Growth of the <hi>Roman</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, which, from a little Root, ſpread its Flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Branches almoſt over every Quarter of the Earth. The Prophet <hi>Daniel</hi> ſpeaks of it at Large in the Two laſt Chapters of his Book, in which he plainly Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tells the Diſſolution of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Government, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with their Laws, Temple, and their Beloved City of <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi> Nor is it unknown, from di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Proofs, that thoſe things came to paſs, and that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:105395:9"/>the Prophecies relating to it, were Fullfill'd even to a Lettrr. 'Twere endleſs to Recount thoſe many Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidential Occurrences which Related to, and Attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed our Bleſſed Saviour's Appearance, and which cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſuch Variety of Events in the World; and we may Obſerve amongſt thoſe many other Refin'd Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines in His Firſt Sermon on the <hi>Mount,</hi> He Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaints his Diſciples with, and Aſſerts the Nature of Providence; and that 'tis concern'd in the moſt Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute Things, How much more in Greater, in the more Important Affairs of Publick Communities and Kingdoms? Nay, our Bleſſed Saviour Reproves, and Corrects their Faithleſs and Miſtruſtful Thoughts re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to it. But to Return.</p>
            <p>What Alterations was not the <hi>Roman</hi> Government ſubject to, before it arriv'd to its Fear'd and Admir'd Greatneſs? And what Convulſions did it not Labour under afterwards? But the Learned Dr. <hi>Howell,</hi> in the Second Part of his General Hiſtory, Judiciouſly Reflects on the Wiſdom and Policy of their Laws, and obſerves them more eſpecially tending to Secure the Rights and Liberties of the People. Yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the great Care, Conduct, Courage, and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience in all thoſe things that were Neceſſary for its Support, we find this Tottering Empire to have had the ſame Diſſolution with thoſe that went before, and which thoſe ſhall have at their Appointed time which ſucceed it.</p>
            <p>I cannot paſs by in Silence an Important and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent Obſervation from Father <hi>Paul</hi>'s Hiſtory of the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> That, notwithſtanding the Cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Intreagues manag'd by that Pack'd Caball of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:105395:10"/>many of them Titular, and who were ſent thither with Inſtructions, to Oppoſe and Hinder all Reformation of Religion, and to Promote the Intereſts of <hi>Rome;</hi> that they were ſo far from attaining their Intended Ends, that on the contrary the Reformation was very much Advanc'd by it. The Doctrines and Articles there Decreed, being directly Oppoſite and Contrary to thoſe of Chriſt, and his Apoſtles; and notwithſtanding 'twas deſign'd, and in the Reſolutions of the Empire and the <hi>French,</hi> to Extirpate what they falſely call'd the Northern Hereſie: Yet the Temporal Intereſts of the Empire ſo far prevail'd, as to oblige them to joyn with the Proteſtant Princes, and to Protect and give Liberty to the Reformers; By which means the Reformation was Eſtabliſh'd, and conſequently Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted and Propagated by its Profeſs'd Enemies.</p>
            <p>To Remark this Providential Diſpenſation, directs me to that Exclamatory Admiration of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> in the 11th of the <hi>Romans,</hi> the 33d and 34th <hi>Verſes. O the depth of the Riches both of the Wiſdom and Knowledge of God! How unſearchable are his Judgments, and his ways past finding out! For who hath known the Mind of the Lord, or who hath been his Counſellor?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have ſo large a Field of Matter before me, that my time obliges me to ſtop here, and paſs to the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Point Propos'd to be Inſiſted on.</p>
            <p>To Reflect on, and Apply the Words of my Text, with Reference to the Solemnity of this Day; <hi>They that ſee thee, ſhall narrowly look upon,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:105395:10"/>
            <p>Tho' the Parallel between the great Monarch of <hi>Aſſyria</hi> and the preſent <hi>French</hi> King, will not hold good in every particular Circumſtance, inaſmuch as the former was hurl'd from a long enjoy'd <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> Monarchy; and the other remov'd from a part only of his Deſign'd Weſtern Monarchy; yet this Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is more particularly Remarkable, That at the ſame time that his Armies were Victorious in the Field, he was Imploring a Peace at the Treaty, and could not Procure a Tolerable one, without Re-deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering his Conqueſts.</p>
            <p>An Inſtance which is not to be found in any Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory; and which, by the way, makes it Difficult to Reconcile the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Paris</hi>'s <hi>Te Deum's;</hi> He Thanks God for his Maſters Taking of Towns, at the Expence of almoſt Ten thouſand Men; and, in ſome ſhort time, was Thanking God for the Peace which forc'd him to Reſtre them for Nothing. But perhaps it was in his Intention to Thank God that put it into his Maſters Heart to make ſo Abſolutely neceſſary, though in all Outward Appearance, ſo Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantageous a Peace, leaſt a Worſe Thing had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallen him.</p>
            <p>Which Reflection upon the Whole, makes thoſe, who were Deceiv'd with Outward Appearances, in ſtead of Subſtance and Realities, look narrowly on thee, and conſider thee; Nay, they are extreamly Surpriz'd to ſee thee Stripp'd, like the Bird in the Fable, who, before every one had pluckt their borrow'd Feathers, appear'd Rich and Gay.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:105395:11"/>
            <p>'Twill puzle the <hi>French</hi> Oratours and Panegyriſts, to find, or contrive a Topick for their Flatteries; They may ſay indeed, Their Great Maſter hath Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Peace to Europe; tho, at the ſame time, we, and all Europe knows, He was Begging it at Our Own Doors; and, 'tis odds, but the Heretick Criticks will be apt to ſuſpect ſome difference, between the words, Giving, and Begging.</p>
            <p>They may, perhaps, Aſcribe that to His Generoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which his Impotent Ambition, and Exhauſted Treaſures (which Enervates all the Motion and Power of Armies) could no longer maintain and ſecure. If to his Juſtice, Why doth he not Reſtore the Remaining part of the Cities and Territories now in his Poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, to which he hath no better Title than to the other? and which, perhaps, one Day, may be the Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of a Greater Refunding.</p>
            <p>If they Applaud his Good Nature, then their Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries will be Cruel indeed, when they cannot but behold him ſtill Ungratefully Perſiſting to Perſecute his own Proſteſtant Subjects to Death, againſt Humane Nature, Oathes and Edicts, who formerly Freely Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd their Lives to ſet the Crown of <hi>France</hi> on his Head.</p>
            <p>And here I cannot but enlarge this Reflection, that nothing hath contributed ſo much to the lowring of <hi>France</hi> as this Perſecution. And 'twas the Opinion of a great General and States-man, the Father of this preſent Elector of <hi>Brandenburgh</hi> (who, in memory to his Honour be it ſpoken, gave the moſt kind and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:105395:11"/>Chriſtian Reception to the poor miſerable Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Refugees) I ſay 'twas his Opinion, That the <hi>French</hi> King would not have receiv'd ſo great a loſs in one of his beſt Armies, as he did by that Unjuſt and Unchriſtian Perſecution, which is fully confirm'd in the event and too late to be retreiv'd: for his moſt Induſtrious Subjects being moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politickly forc'd away from their Native Soil, and Habitations, withdrew their Effects, carry'd away, and ſet up the <hi>French</hi> Manufactures whereever they ſettled, which ſupply'd thoſe places and others, all which were formerly made and ſent from <hi>France;</hi> by which means <hi>France</hi> is become at preſent both Impoveriſh'd and Uninhabited.</p>
            <p>Which Reflection perhaps confirms the unob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd, but Juſt and Admirable Method of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, that the Pride and Power of <hi>France</hi> which could not be humbled and leſſen'd by any Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federated forreign Force, ſhould be laid low and given up, occaſion'd by his <hi>own</hi> infatuated Counſels and Barbarouſly executed commands: He may palliate and conceal for ſome time his skin'd Wound, but in the Body Politick as well as the Natural, where the Diſeaſe is Hectical, as ſoon as it ſhews it ſelf it becomes Mortal.</p>
            <p>Thus they, who now ſee thee at Home in thy preſent State and Condition, ſhall for the future only eſteem thee <hi>Mortal,</hi> a Match but for a few, ſubject to the Viciſſitudes of Fortune, to Paſſions and Vices like other Men: and thy quondam Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirers and Adorers amongſt us, ſhall narrowly look
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:105395:12"/>on thee and conſider thee ſaying, Is this the Man in whom <hi>we</hi> put ſo much Confidence, whoſe Dragoons we every day expected to reſtore our Rights, preſerve our Laws, and to Eſtabliſh the Church of <hi>England</hi> in the Purity of its Doctrines? Is the noiſe of his All-ſhakeing Artillery Ceas'd, and the Neighing of his Horſes prepar'd for Battle now heard no more? And are all the flattring Hopes, of the Honours and Eſtates, we promis'd our ſelves for Betraying our own Country, thus Defeated?</p>
            <p>Theſe conſiderations fill us with Indignation and Amazement, nor can it, like the Bleſſed Virgin in the Goſpel, upon another miraculous occaſion enter into our Hearts <hi>How theſe things ſhould be,</hi> or come to paſs.</p>
            <p>But thus it is; and this is the Day, the Happy Day, ſet apart to offer up our humble and hearty thanks to God for it. A Day which we had little reaſon to expect, when by our Cauſeleſs, but wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Murmurrings and Repinings, we had ſo ſoon un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratefully forgotten the train of paſt Providences which laid a foundation for it, and when our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vokeing Sins had ſo loudly call'd for Deſtruction, inſtead of ſo great, and undeſerv'd a Bleſſing. A Day which ſurpriz'd our diſtant Expectations, nay which ſome amongſt us thought Impoſſible, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed would have been ſo, if they had had but Power ſufficient to have Enſlav'd themſelves and us, Men who were reſtleſs and uneaſy in their Tempers, Men who were unreaſonable, and would, be ſatisfied with nothing but Contradictions, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:105395:12"/>Power, and Property, Father <hi>Peters,</hi> and no Popery. Nay they would have perſwaded us that <hi>French</hi> Shooes and Fetters would have worn and ſet eaſy on us.</p>
            <p>Theſe Men, I think, have moſt reaſon to be highly Thankful, ſince by this Advantageous Peace, they are deliver'd from themſelves, and made happy even againſt their own Wills.</p>
            <p>Our Neighbouring Allies and Confederates, may now rejoyce and ſit in ſafety and unmoleſted in their own reſtor'd Cities and Territories; they may deſervedly Triumph for this laſt Campaine, in that they have gain'd ſo much without loſs or hazard: And as they have always admir'd, and applauded; the Courage and Conduct of their great General and Head in the Feild, ſo they have good reaſon to own him no leſs powerful in his Sagacious Management of this Victorious Peace in his Cloſſet.</p>
            <p>It muſt be Divinely inſpir'd Wiſdome, that could Engage, Unite, and Cement, ſo many thwarting and divided Intereſts, which in the end hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur'd this, 'tis to be hop'd for, laſting Peace; the cheif Author of which doth this day aſcribe and acknowledge the Glory of it to the Great God of Peace, and is well contented with the ſelf-ſatisfaction of having been the Inſtrument of ſo much good to Mankind, his cheifeſt joy is to ſee his Friends and Allies lie in Glory, every one in his own Houſe, where they may ſecurely gaze and reflect on their Reduc'd Enemy and ſay.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:105395:13"/>
            <p>Is there a Stop put to thy Devaſtations, and can we now quietly Replant, Sow, and Rebuild our burnt Habitations, Ruin'd Fields, and deſtroyed Groves? And ſhall our Country, which is become as a Willderneſs, once more Flouriſh and be Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited? Are thy Deſtructions at an end, and ſhall our Cities once again riſe up more Glorious from their dreadful Flames? And ſhall our Subjects de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd as Priſoners, return to their Native Countries, like the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> from their hard and <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> Bondage; theſe are Bleſſings which fill our Hearts with Gladneſs, and which Summon all our grateful Thanks and acknowledgement. Whilſt thou, like the Eclips'd Sun, lookſt Black, and Mourn, and haſt now leiſure to Murmur and Repine at thy un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pity'd Fall.</p>
            <p>As we have been all ſurrounded with Fears and Dangers, ſo now we are amidſt the Joyful Accla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations of Peace, the Souldiers are glad, in that they have out-liv'd the preſſing Miſeries, and Dangers of Sieges and Camps, the Merchants rejoyce becauſe they have no other Enemys to deal withall, but the Rowling Billows and inconſtant Winds. Inſtead of the ſhrill and rugged noiſe of Drums and Trumpets, our Ears are now carreſs'd and gratify'd with the more ſmooth and ſoft Inſtruments of Peace. There ſhall be no more Weeping Mothers, nor Diſtreſs'd Orphans, the Effects of Cruel and Deadly War. But Wine which make glad the Heart of Man, and Oil to make him a Cheerful Countenance, and all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Plenty ſhall now abound, the Effects of Peace.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:105395:13"/>
            <p>For theſe Mercies, we will all, with our Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Voices, ſay, with the Prophet <hi>David,</hi> in the 103 Pſalm, <hi>Bleſs the Lord, O my Soul: and all that is within me bleſs his Holy Name. Bleſs the Lord, O my Soul, and forget not all his Benefits. Who redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth thy Life from destruction, who Crowneth thee with loving kindneſs and tender Mercies. The Lord execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth Righteouſneſs and Judgment for all that are Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis an Unſpeakable Happineſs, that God hath ſo order'd our Religious Duties, as to be our True Intereſt; Our Prayers ſerve to procure us preſent Bleſſings, and our due Thanks and Praiſes for thoſe Receiv'd, are as an Earneſt for Future.</p>
            <p>Yet there are ſome Unthankful Perſons (which ſeems ſcarcely credible) whom neither the Favours of God or Men can Oblige: There is an Inveterate Malignity in their Tempers, like thoſe Unhappy Conſtitutions, which turn the Wholſomeſt Food into Crudities and Diſeaſes; they are a Plague in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed to themſelves, which is their Puniſhment: their Malice preys on their Invenom'd Spirits; and, like the Angry Bee, as Naturaliſts tells us, the ſlight Wound they give another, proves fatal to themſelves.</p>
            <p>To Conclude the Whole. Let this, almoſt Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal, Peace, Perſwade us to Reconcile and Unite our Love and Affections towards each other. We have but one Common Intereſt to Preſerve, which
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:105395:14"/>comprehends what is moſt dear to us, our Lives, Liberties, and Religion; which our Reconcil'd E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy, in a late Article, Openly ſtrikes at.</p>
            <p>Let us not be Amus'd, and Prepoſſeſs'd with the Plauſible Opinions of any Private Perſons; but leave all Matters, relating to our Future Wellfare, to the Wiſdom of the Great Council of the Nation, now to be Aſſembled; whoſe Tranſactions, I Pray God Direct, for the Publick Good.</p>
            <p>Let us be Cautious, and not flatter our ſelves too ſecure, when 'tis in our Power to make our ſelves ſafe, leaſt we become an eaſier Prey to thoſe, who may prove ſuch Treacherous <hi>Friends,</hi> as King <hi>David</hi> Experienc'd, who Speak Peace with their Mouths, whilſt they have War in their Hearts, and make themſelves Ready for Battel.</p>
            <p>God hath given us a Prince, who hath Courage to Speak the Truth from his Heart, and who makes our Intereſt his own; He hath Valour enough to Oppoſe all his Enemies, whether Forreign or Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtick; and whoſe Glorious Actions evidently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate, 'tis not ours alone he purſues, but, like his Great Protectour, the more extenſive Happineſs of Mankind.</p>
            <p>Wherefore laying aſide all Differences and Preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices, private Piques and Animoſities, let us Una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimouſly concur, with our Hearty Endeavours, to Eſtabliſh His Throne in Peace and Security, that
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:105395:14"/>our <hi>Lawfull</hi> and <hi>Rightfull</hi> KING, who hath Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Expos'd Himſelf to, and Conquer'd all Difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Dangers, for the Honour and Safety of the Nation, may, for the Future, Enjoy the Dear-Bought Pleaſures, (if any there be) who hitherto hath onely had the Troubles and Fatigues, of a Crown.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
